<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Direct road to peace and happiness in church and state</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1525A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26699</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09523530</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09523530</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43472</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36048)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1329:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Direct road to peace and happiness in church and state</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43472:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIRECT ROAD, TO Peace and Happineſs, IN <hi>Church and State.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 13.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher Power, for there is no Power but of God: The Powers that be are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JER. 7.</hi> Verſe <hi>3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Amend your Ways, and your Doings; if you throughly execute Judgment between a Man and his Neighbour; if you oppreſs not the Stranger, the Fatherleſs, and the Widdow, and ſhed not innocent Blood in this Place, neither walk after other Gods to your Hurt, I will cauſe you to dwell in this Place.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:43472:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43472:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Will not trouble the Reader with the Arguments uſed, either for or againſt my publiſhing the enſuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe; for in truth I ſuſpect too many Perſons reſemble Apes (making uſe of the Gats feet to ſave their own) and as many more rather inclined to Revenge Injuries, or Quarrelling with Perſons for their Offices; than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs Crimes, or their Brethrens Grievances; and the Judgment of Friends, or near Relations, may be ſuſpected to be Partial: So that I hold it beſt to adviſe with none, in matters of this nature, but ſuch as are of the <hi>Heathen Philoſophers Opinion</hi> in this (viz.) <hi>That we are not born for our ſelves, but partly for our Country.</hi> And the Character which King <hi>Henry IV.</hi> (in his laſt Speech to his Son) gave of the People of <hi>England,</hi> holds true; <hi>That they are Wiſe, Stout, and True-hearted, if Rich, and Juſtly dealt with, and Religiouſly governed: But if Poor and Oppreſſed, they will Rebel.</hi> Their Wiſdom is ſhewn by the Excellency of their Laws and Conſtitutions<note n="(a)" place="margin">Stat. de Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogativa Regis 17 Edw. 1. 1 Hen. 4. Cap. 6. 1 Eliz. 1.</note> for ſecuring the <hi>Royal Eſtate,</hi> and their own <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> and <hi>Properties:</hi> Time would fail me to ſhew what Proviſion is made, that the Crown and People may be well ſerved; and how early after the Reformation the People reſtored<note n="(b)" place="margin">27 Hen. 8. Cap. 24.</note> the Ancient Rights, Prerogative, and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of Juſtice to the Crown, which were ſevered from it in Times of <hi>Popiſh Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> that the
<pb facs="tcp:43472:3"/>Adminiſtration might be free and undiſturbed with Rivals for the future: And what care is taken for the Election<note n="(c)" place="margin">31 Eliz. Cap. 6.</note> of Schollars, and to provide againſt <hi>Symony,</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">12 Rich. 2. Cap. 2.5 &amp; 6 Edw. 6. Cap. 16. 2 Hen. 6. Cap. 10.</note> and againſt Buying and Selling Offices; that Benefices and Places of Truſt may be given to none but Perſons Worthy and Meet, and not to any for <hi>Money, Brocage, Favour</hi> or <hi>Affection:</hi> And how<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Eliz. Cap. 1. 5 Eliz. Cap. 1. 3 Jac. 1. Cap. 7. 7 Jac. 1. Cap. 6. 25 Car. 2. Cap. 2. &amp; 7 &amp; 8 Will. 3.</note> all in Military as well as Civil Imployments, are obliged to take Oaths, enjoyning them to be true to their Truſt; and that no Man ſhall be Judge or Jury-man in any Matter where his own Interest may incline him to be Partial or Unjuſt: And how<note n="(f)" place="margin">22 &amp; 23 Car. 2. Cap. 22.4 &amp; 5 Will. 3. Cont. 6 &amp; 7 Will. 3.</note> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures being ſetled, are to be duly anſwered to for the Benefit of Diſcoverers, and to Charitable Uſes, alſo to be a Revenue to the Crown, for doing it felf and People<note n="(g)" place="margin">13 Edw. 1. Cap. 50.</note> Juſtice: And what Liberty the Crown hath to ſupply all Defects in the Execution of the Laws, to make them anſwer their true end; Alſo to Reward and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don whom it thinks fit; And how the King, and all in Authority under him, are obliged to puniſh none, but as the Laws provide: The People well knowing, That when the Crown ſuffers great Loſs and Damage, by the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Unskillful, or by the Neglects, or Frauds, or Perjuries of the most Knowing in Office, it will occaſion new Aids and Taxes to be laid on many: And that the generality of Mankind love to be freed from Duties; And that nothing more Diſcontents the People, than when they ſee, that it is not Perſons with most Right, but longeſt Purſe, or powerful Friends prevail, or that even Right and Juſtice is not done to Poor and Rich, without reſpect of Perſons, as<note n="(h)" place="margin">20 Edw. 3. Cap. 1.</note> the Laws pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide: We all know, that wrong Doers will bandy to ſave themſelves, and Perſons injured will ſeek redreſs; and if they fail of their Ends, the firſt by Deſign, and the latter by Miſtake, may impute their Grievanies to wrong Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:43472:3"/>and Cauſes, and overthrow the Government which would ſet us all to Rights. 'Tis freſh in Memory, That the Abuſes put upon Wards and others, by the Court of Wards and Star-Chamber, occaſioned the never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Rebellion in <hi>1641,</hi> which many thouſand Perſons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and whole Families, wofully experienced, who were not Guilty of the ſaid Abuſes, unleſs in being Remiſs or Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent to chuſe worthy Perſons to ſerve in <hi>Parliament,</hi> or that the <hi>Perſons Choſen,</hi> did not timely Redreſs their <hi>Brethrens Grievances.</hi> And the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> who ever had the Reputation of <hi>Stout,</hi> have in this Effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and degenerated Age, ſignalized their <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Valour</hi> againſt the Common Enemy of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> never had a King more reſigned to the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt</hi> of his <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> than His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty upon all Occaſions hath declared himſelf to be; And we never had more <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Learned Biſhops,</hi> nor more Knowing <hi>Privy Counſellors</hi> and <hi>Judges;</hi> nor a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty</hi> more freely left to their own <hi>Liberty</hi> to chuſe their <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> to Redreſs their <hi>Grievances;</hi> Nor more frequent <hi>Parliaments,</hi> nor longer <hi>Seſſions;</hi> Yet <hi>Diſcontents</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> abound unmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurably: And from the <hi>Experience</hi> of a <hi>Grave</hi> and <hi>Learned Judge,</hi> who tells us,<note place="margin">Preface of Judge <hi>Davy</hi>'s Reports.</note> 
               <hi>That the Law ſees no Enormities, but by the Watchful Eyes of Diligent Officers:</hi> We may infer, That we may Wander and Periſh in the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> of our <hi>Diſcontents,</hi> if our <hi>Spy-alls</hi> be <hi>Negligent, Ignorant, Unskillful, Falſe</hi> and <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous:</hi> One would think that the heavy Judgments which befel the <hi>falſe Spies,</hi> and the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by their <hi>evil Reports;</hi> And the <hi>Reward</hi> of <hi>Caleb</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, ſhould be a <hi>Warning</hi> to all now living, to be <hi>True</hi> to their <hi>Truſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43472:4"/>
            <p>I have been a <hi>Sorrowful Spectator</hi> for ſome Years, of the <hi>Miſeries</hi> my <hi>Native Country</hi> hath languiſhed under, by <hi>Diviſions</hi> and <hi>Debaucheries</hi> in <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> and the <hi>Helliſh Contrivances</hi> of our Enemies. And being under the <hi>Sacred Obligation</hi> of <hi>Oaths</hi> to ſerve <hi>His Majeſty</hi> according to the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> of the <hi>Realm;</hi> and taught, as all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are, That they beſt expreſs their <hi>Duty,</hi> when they be <hi>Serviceable Members</hi> as well of the <hi>State</hi> as of the <hi>Church:</hi> And that they are not to put their <hi>Candle</hi> under a <hi>Buſhel,</hi> nor to hide their <hi>Talent</hi> in a <hi>Napkin,</hi> but to communicate their <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> to their <hi>Brethren,</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring them that are in <hi>Bonds</hi> as bound with them; and them that <hi>ſuffer Adverſity,</hi> as being themſelves alſo in Body; and well knowing that it is with ſuch who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the <hi>Cure</hi> of a <hi>Sick State,</hi> as it is with <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians</hi> and their <hi>Patients,</hi> The moſt <hi>Skilful Phyſicians</hi> cannot <hi>Cure Diſeaſes</hi> before they know them: If they give <hi>Phyſick</hi> at random, they may as ſoon <hi>Kill</hi> as <hi>Cure;</hi> and <hi>Phyſicians</hi> moſt viſited with <hi>Patients,</hi> have leaſt time to inform themſelves of the <hi>true State</hi> and <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of their moſt <hi>diſtempered Patients;</hi> and ſeeing moſt <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> when diſcovered, may eaſily be cured, if Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of taking <hi>proper Remedies</hi> be not ſlipt. I did upon theſe <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> ſet my ſelf at work to publiſh the enſuing <hi>Treatiſe;</hi> und what I have omitted therein, I would willingly ſupply by this <hi>Preface:</hi> Every <hi>Judicious Perſon</hi> knows, that most <hi>Feuds</hi> and <hi>Diſcontents</hi> are fomented by <hi>Suits in Law, Elections</hi> of <hi>Members</hi> to ſerve in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and beſtowing <hi>Beneſices</hi> and <hi>Places</hi> of <hi>Truſt;</hi> and that when <hi>Diſputes</hi> about any of them happen between <hi>Popular</hi> and <hi>Powerful Antagoniſts;</hi> and the <hi>Deciſion</hi> be no other than <hi>Silencing</hi> the <hi>Parties</hi> worſted for the preſent; it is but <hi>Healing</hi> the <hi>Wounds</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43472:4"/>falſe; and ſhould the ſame <hi>Gangreen</hi> before diſcovered, it may occaſion the <hi>Diſſecting</hi> of <hi>Members,</hi> or <hi>Loſs</hi> of <hi>Lives:</hi> We have had two <hi>Miraculous Revolutions,</hi> viz. The <hi>Reſtauration</hi> of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and the <hi>Coronation</hi> of King <hi>William</hi> the Third; let us (having abuſed the former) make good uſe of the latter.</p>
            <p>Every <hi>Tree</hi> is known by its <hi>Fruit:</hi> May not ſuch as obtain <hi>Benefices</hi> by <hi>Symony,</hi> and their <hi>Benefactors,</hi> be ſuſpected to be in <hi>Confederacy</hi> with ſuch as <hi>Diſpence</hi> with the <hi>Laws</hi> againſt <hi>Buying</hi> and <hi>Selling Places</hi> of <hi>Truſt;</hi> and may not all the <hi>Confederates</hi> be ſuſpected to be Supine and Negligent in all things, but what makes for their own <hi>private Intereſt</hi> or <hi>Profit;</hi> and will not ſuch wink at <hi>Miſcarriages,</hi> or highten our <hi>Diſcontents,</hi> and retard the <hi>Redreſs</hi> of their <hi>Brethrens Grievances:</hi> If two or more be <hi>Competitors</hi> for a <hi>Benefice</hi> or an <hi>Office</hi> void, and it be given to one leaſt Deſerving, or hath leaſt need, will not the reſt be diſobliged, eſpecially ſuch as be Impoveriſhed with <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Dutiful Services</hi> to the <hi>Publick;</hi> and may not the <hi>Perſons</hi> diſobliged by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, impute the ſame to wrong <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Cauſes?</hi> Are not ſuch as abuſe <hi>Regalia's</hi> holden of the <hi>Crown Petty Tyrants?</hi> Were not all Benefices and Offices in the ſole Gift of the <hi>Crown,</hi> before diveſted thereof by <hi>Grant</hi> or <hi>Uſurpation?</hi> Do not ſuch as abuſe that <hi>Truſt,</hi> ſell both <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> and make <hi>Religion, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> and <hi>Property, Stalking-horſes</hi> for their <hi>Villain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Purpoſes?</hi> Is not the <hi>right</hi> and <hi>due Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> all we have to depend on, to preſerve us from the <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> of <hi>Home-Tyrants?</hi> And what but the <hi>Propagation</hi> and <hi>Encouragement</hi> of the <hi>Fiſheries,</hi> will increaſe the numbers of fit <hi>Perſons</hi> to be <hi>Sea-men</hi> and <hi>Marriners</hi> to Man our <hi>Ships,</hi> that guard us from <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Tyrants?</hi> And who Obſtructs the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43472:5"/>of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> but ſuch as <hi>Buy</hi> and <hi>Sell Benefices</hi> and <hi>Offices?</hi> And who makes great <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>young Fry</hi> and <hi>Brood</hi> of <hi>Fiſh,</hi> and obſtruct <hi>Navigation,</hi> and hinder the Increaſe of fit <hi>Perſons</hi> to be <hi>Sea-men</hi> and <hi>Marriners,</hi> but ſuch as under the <hi>Umbrage</hi> of <hi>Grants</hi> of <hi>Liberties,</hi> for them, their <hi>Tenants</hi> and <hi>Farmers,</hi> to Fiſh in <hi>Royal</hi> and <hi>Navigable Rivers,</hi> erect <hi>Piles, Stakes, Keddals, Locks,</hi> with ſtrait <hi>Wires</hi> or <hi>Wands, Weres, Dams,</hi> and Lett the ſame; and little <hi>Cottages,</hi> and ſmall parcels of <hi>Land</hi> by ſuch River-ſides, to Farm at ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Rent, and ſuffer their Tenants to Potch and Fiſh at unſeaſonable times, and with unlawful Nets, Engines and Devices: And are not <hi>Salmon</hi> (by their Deſtruction of Fiſh, full of Spawn, and feeding their Swine with the young Brood and Fry) ſold at <hi>12 d.</hi> per Pound in ſome parts, where it was ſold for <hi>1 d.</hi> and large <hi>Silver Eals</hi> at <hi>6 d.</hi> or <hi>8 d. per</hi> piece, where the like was ſold for <hi>1 d.</hi> And will not a <hi>Lamprey-Pye</hi> now coſt <hi>3 l.</hi> or <hi>3 l. 10 s.</hi> where it might have been had for <hi>12</hi> or <hi>13 s.</hi> to the great Diſſatisfaction of the Country-Gentlemen, and the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Poor, to whom Fiſh plentiful and cheap was great Relief: And are not ſome parts of Navigable Rivers, ſo annoyed with <hi>Stakes, Locks, Dams, Weres,</hi> and the like, that Veſſels of <hi>30</hi> Tun cannot (where Veſſels of <hi>100</hi> Tun uſed to) paſs and repaſs: And have not ſuch <hi>Tenants</hi> and <hi>Farmers,</hi> for the Lucre of <hi>Wrecks,</hi> Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered poor <hi>Sea-men</hi> and <hi>Marriners</hi> that were eſcaping to ſhoar: And how many poor Fiſher-men, taken Fiſhing in places within the compaſs or ſpace where <hi>Pretenders</hi> to <hi>Royalties</hi> claim any thing of Fiſhing, have been ſo ill treated by <hi>Farmers, Stewards,</hi> or <hi>Agents</hi> to <hi>Vice-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals</hi> and <hi>Juſtices of Peace,</hi> that the <hi>Fiſher-men</hi> who took ſeveral <hi>Apprentices,</hi> have been forced to betake themſelves to other Imployments ever ſince their uſage
<pb facs="tcp:43472:5"/>was ſo bad, by ſuch who ingroſſed the most convenient places of <hi>Fiſhing</hi> in <hi>Royal</hi> and <hi>Navigable Rivers,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Umbrage</hi> of <hi>Grants</hi> of <hi>Free-Fiſheries</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. Certainly ſuch <hi>Vice-Admirals</hi> and <hi>Juſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of Peace,</hi> as are Owners of Houſes and Land near ſuch Rivers, who pretend to ſuch Liberties, cannot but know, that all the <hi>Ground, Soile</hi> and <hi>Fiſhery,</hi> in <hi>Navigable Rivers,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bant</hi> Caſe or the Caſe of Royal Rivers. <hi>Davis</hi> Rep. fol. 56.</note> are the Inheritance of the Crown, as well where the <hi>Water</hi> at uſual <hi>Spring-Tides</hi> cover the Ground, as where the <hi>Water</hi> runs and no Tides come; for that reaſon the City of <hi>London</hi> enjoy the ſame in <hi>Thames,</hi> as far as <hi>Stanes-bridge,</hi> by <hi>Grants</hi> from the <hi>Crown,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by <hi>Act of Parliament:</hi> And do not private <hi>Rivers</hi> ceaſe to be private when made Navigable at the Counties Charge by <hi>Act of Parliament:</hi> And are not all <hi>Nuſances</hi> in <hi>Private Rivers,</hi> relating to the Publick, and for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the Deſtruction of the young Brood and Fry of Fiſh, to be redreſſed by the King, or ſuch as His Majeſty intruſts, where Lords of Royalties and Franchiſes are Remiſs or Negligent. And do not ſuch as have only <hi>Free Liberty</hi> or <hi>Licenſe</hi> to <hi>Fiſh</hi> in <hi>Navigable Royal Rivers</hi> abuſe their <hi>Liberty,</hi> in caſe they hinder others Lawfully Authorized to Fiſh? Doth not the Statute <hi>21 Jacobi 1. Cap. 2.</hi> which limiteth the Crown not to Sue for Lands or Hereditaments concealed by the ſpace of ſixty years, ſave its Rights to recover <hi>Franchiſes</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> holden by <hi>Uſurpation</hi> or <hi>Wrong?</hi> If a Subject grant leave to<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Munj y</hi> and <hi>Brown</hi>'s Caſe, Inſt. fol. 165.</note> another to dig in his Ground, may he not dig himſelf, or appoint others to dig alſo? And is not the Inheritance of the Crown, and its Royal Eſtate, as well ſecured, as any private Subject can pretend his own Eſtate or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty to be ſecured? Are not all Vice-Admirals prohibited to meddle<note n="(c)" place="margin">13 Rich. 2. Cap. 5.</note> with any thing done within the Realm, but what are done upon the Sea? So that although Rivers be
<pb facs="tcp:43472:6"/>very broad and Salt near the Sea: Yet are not all Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences and Treſpaſſes done or committed in ſuch <hi>Rivers,</hi> properly determinable <hi>infra Corpus Comitatus,</hi> where <hi>Vice-Admirals</hi> have nothing to do: And Juſtices of Peace ought to know, That <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> wherein the King is not named,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Inſt. fol. 43.</note> ſhall not take away the King's Right; And<note n="(e)" place="margin">Dyer 225. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rep. 146.</note> that <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> impowering Juſtices of Peace to do what the King hath Right to do, ſhall not bar or hinder the King to do it; ſuch Acts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing intended to eaſe the King of Labour, not to debar or deprive him of his <hi>Rights, Power</hi> or <hi>Prerogative,</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Inſt. 1 part fol. 119.2 part fol. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> which is the moſt eſſential part of the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> And it's reſolved,<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bans</hi> Caſe, or the Caſe of Royal Rivers. <hi>Davis</hi> Rep. fol. 56.</note> That the King may at this day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point a Water-Bayliff of all or any his <hi>Royal Rivers:</hi> And all <hi>Sages</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> agree, That <hi>His Majeſty</hi> may Erect and Grant a <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Record,</hi> to hold <hi>Plea</hi> of what <hi>His Majeſty's</hi> other <hi>Courts</hi> hold <hi>Plea</hi> of; and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point reaſonable <hi>Fees</hi> to ſupport the ſame. Yet <hi>Vice-Admirals</hi> and <hi>Juſtices of Peace</hi> near <hi>Severn,</hi> diſpute the <hi>King's Prerogative,</hi> and the <hi>Water-Bayliffs Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> in that <hi>River,</hi> which Office appears by <hi>Records</hi> in the <hi>Tower</hi> to be very Ancient: But what may not ſome by <hi>Miſtake,</hi> and others in point of <hi>Intereſt,</hi> be guilty of? I have reaſon to believe, that had not <hi>His Majeſty's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors</hi> granted the <hi>Inheritance</hi> of the <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Bayliff</hi> of <hi>Thames,</hi> to the powerful City of <hi>London, Uſurpations, Nuſances</hi> and <hi>Treſpaſſes</hi> had ſwarmed in that <hi>River,</hi> as they do in other <hi>Royal Navigable Rivers.</hi> What ſignifie our <hi>Laws</hi> declaring, That<note n="(h)" place="margin">13 &amp; 14 Car. 2. Cap. 28.</note> the <hi>Publick Honour, Wealth</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> of this <hi>Realm,</hi> as well in the <hi>Maintenance</hi> and <hi>Support</hi> of <hi>Navigation,</hi> as in many other reſpects depend on the <hi>Improvement</hi> and <hi>Encouragement</hi> of the <hi>Fiſhery:</hi> And the many <hi>Laws</hi> in force for the <hi>Preſervation</hi> of the young Brood, and Fry
<pb facs="tcp:43472:6"/>of <hi>Fiſh;</hi> And to hinder <hi>Royal</hi> and <hi>Navigable Rivers</hi> to be choaked up with <hi>Filth,</hi> or annoyed with ought that may obſtruct <hi>Navigation:</hi> Nay indeed what ſignifie all our wholſome <hi>Laws</hi> to ſecure our <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> if a ſtop be not put to ſuch as recommend unfit Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to Places of Truſt? I verily believe, that ſuch as diſpence with <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> and magnifie the <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of their <hi>Parties,</hi> by Trading with Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Places of Trust, as the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Prieſts</hi> Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick with <hi>Pardons</hi> and <hi>Indulgences,</hi> are Conſcious to themſelves, That they are no true Subjects to the King of <hi>Great Britain:</hi> And that they and their <hi>Parties,</hi> are but a handful of Men, compared with the vaſt Numbers of good Subjects grieved with their <hi>Frauds</hi> and <hi>Perjuries.</hi> If ought I propoſe for a <hi>Cure</hi> of our <hi>Diſcontents</hi> be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, I ſubmit the ſame to be ſupplied by the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of the <hi>Government;</hi> and becauſe every <hi>Subject,</hi> as a <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> is bound to ſerve the Head, and 'tis eaſier to add to an <hi>Invention,</hi> than to find out how or which way to make the firſt <hi>Eſſay,</hi> I have communicated my <hi>Propoſals</hi> in a plain and familiar Language to my <hi>Country-men,</hi> that the weakeſt Capacity may judge of them, and propoſe his own, which he thinks better, having experienced what unlikely Perſons have done: Who would believe, did not <hi>Records</hi> witneſs, that a <hi>Soldier</hi> ſhould invent <hi>Printing,</hi> and a <hi>Monk Guns:</hi> And I know that the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Lords-Juſtices,</hi> being buſily imploy'd about <hi>weighty Affairs,</hi> want Leiſure to read my <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</hi> However ſome <hi>Judicious Readers</hi> may happily agree with me, and have opportunity to give <hi>His Majeſty</hi> or the <hi>Lords-Juſtices</hi> to underſtand, that a <hi>Regiſtry</hi> of the Names of Perſons doing <hi>Good Services,</hi> orderly kept, and rewarding them duly, and the <hi>Reports</hi> or <hi>Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations</hi> of <hi>Societies</hi> for ſupplying Vacancies of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43472:7"/>and <hi>Offices,</hi> where none in the <hi>Regiſtry</hi> be fit for the ſame, will make the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>People</hi> be well ſerved: And that if the ſame be not done, or ſome other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay found out, to avoid the <hi>Secret Intreagues</hi> which paſs all <hi>Underſtanding</hi> between <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Officers,</hi> and <hi>Obſcure Perſons,</hi> who abuſe Noble Perſons and others, that have the Diſpoſition of Benefices and Places of Truſt, the Avenues of Juſtice will be ſtopt. I had made <hi>Coin</hi> and <hi>Bullion</hi> part of the ſubject Matter of my enſuing <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,</hi> but that the <hi>Lords-Juſtices</hi> iſſued out their <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> to ſupply the Defects of the Laws relating thereto, by promiſing a Reward of a Moiety to Diſcoverers; but it is to be feared, there are ſo many ſecret ways of convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Coin</hi> and <hi>Bullion</hi> out of the Realm, in Packs of Cloth, and Casks, with Liquors, and the like, that unleſs Coin and Bullion be made more valuable here, if but one Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in an Ounce, than in any other part of the World, the Exportation will hardly be prevented: However I am glad to ſee the Government ſenſible of the Neceſſity of rewarding and encouraging Diſcoverers, becauſe they run unſpeakable Hazards, by diſcovering the undue Practices of ill Men, who we know will both give and take Bribes, and leave no Device or Trick untried, to take away the Lives, Eſtates and Reputation of Diſcoverers, and to ſtifle their moſt true and faithful Diſcoveries and Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals; for that reaſon I had rather leave ſuch Self-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted Ill-principled Perſons to gueſs at my Name, than know it by Subſcription: And ſeeing there is no Man living, but what is envied by ſome; and that a Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice entertained againſt a Perſon, will hinder ſome Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to profit by his Works, upon that account alſo, and by what King <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaw or experienced,<note place="margin">Eccl. 9. v. 13 to the end.</note> I hold it beſt to ſubſcribe no Name,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>VALE.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43472:7"/>
            <head>A Direct Road, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>READER, I foreſee, ſome will Object,<note place="margin">1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rich</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5 and 6 <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 6. Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>That 'tis impoſſible to ſupply the Defects of the Laws, for having Perſons Worthy and Meet, and none other, advanced to Offices;</hi> Therefore I deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thus, That all things are to be held poſſible and performable, which may be accompliſhed by ſome Perſons, though not by every one: And which may be done by the United Labours of many, tho not by one a part: And in brief, which may be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the Care and Charge of the Publick, tho not by the Abilities and Induſtry of private Perſons. If for all this there be any, would rather take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, That of <hi>Solomon, Dicit piger Leo eſt in via,</hi> Than that of <hi>Virgil, Poſſunt quia poſſe videntur:</hi> It is enough for me, if my Labours may be eſteemed Votes, or rather, the better ſort of Wiſhes: For as it asks ſome Knowledge to demand a Queſtion, not imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent; ſo it requires ſome Underſtanding to make a Wiſh, not abſurd.</p>
            <p>I wiſh all Men were true Proteſtants; And that all His Majeſties Free-born and Naturalized Subjects underſtood the Law, which ſaith, <hi>That their King is the Father of their Country; The Fountain of Juſtice, and the Patron and Protector of that Church, which is endowed with universal Charity: The very Bond of Peace and all Vertues, without which, whoſoever liveth, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted dead before God:</hi> None queſtions the Kings Legal Power, or who made him King; but ſuch as are of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> kidney, that queſtioned <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43472:8"/>who made him a Ruler and a Judge, and cauſed him to fly his Country for doing a Brotherly Office.</p>
            <p>The King is a wiſe Prince and a profeſt Proteſtant, had he time to read the Caſe, and Petitions of his meaneſt Subjects, he would certainly do them ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and cheap Juſtice, It is his Misfortune, as well as thine: That he is buſily imployed, <hi>Circa Ardua negotia regni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Heathen Philoſopher, that could ſay, <hi>We are not born for our ſelves, but partly for our Country,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns all Free-born and Naturalized Subjects (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as are under the obligation of Oaths and Aſſociations to be true to his Majeſty and his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) that are not as ſerviceable as they may, or can be. Can any profeſt Proteſtant be ungrateful to His Majeſty, that calls to mind, the many eminent Dangers, both by Sea and Land, to which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Sacred Perſon hath been ſo often expoſed, to ſecure Proteſtants from <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> and <hi>Popery?</hi> and ſees how freely His Majeſty leaves all things to be ſetled and done in <hi>Parliament</hi> for the common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Crown and People: So that if we be not wanting to our ſelves, we may be as happy as we can hope to be in this World and the next.</p>
            <p>Therefore Reader, I will offer to thee ſuch things, as I conceive neceſſary to be Communicated for the Service of my King and Country: If any thing be diſliked, or not well approved on, let thy Charity pardon me, it being well intended; and remember it was not the Widows Mite, but her willing Mind to Contribute more, made her Preſent acceptable: Let not private Intereſt, Favour, or Affection, ſway thy Judgmeent; read diligently, and judge Impartially, and give grains of Allowance to thy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43472:8"/>weak Brother, who exhorts thee in the Apoſtles words; <hi>Remember them that are in Bonds, as bound with them, and them that ſuffer Adverſity, as being thy ſelf alſo in the Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In private Families ſhould the Husband Command unreaſonable things, or the Wife deſpute her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands reaſonable Juriſdiction, or the Children their Parents, or the Servants be Judges in their own Caſe, what diſtraction would inevitably enſue, in caſe Law and Equity were not Umpire.</p>
            <p>Art thou compelled to take Oaths, and Subſcribe Aſſociations, thou art bound and thou muſt obey, or ſuffer what the Law Inflicts for thy diſobedience; if thou diſcharge thy Oath and Duty, and ſuffer any loſs or damage for thy Obedience, the Government is bound to make the repairation and to Protect thee: If a Law be attended with Inconveniences which were not foreſeen at the time of making, and thou art proſecuted by force thereof, the King can ſtop proceedings, until the <hi>Parliament</hi> meet to Annul it, or Amend what is therein Amiſs. Art thou O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the neglect, or <hi>Non Execution</hi> of any whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Law, the King can Command the due <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of it? Haſt thou Conſumed thy Eſtate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted great Debts in diſcharge of Oath and Duty, and doſt thou want Subſiſtence for thy felf and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and will not thy Creditors forbear troubling and reſtraining thee of thy Liberty, and will not the Government relieve thee? Commit thy Cauſe to God, he is the relief of the Opreſſed, and can make thy caſe known to the King, as he did <hi>Mordecais</hi> to King <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> Doth any in Authority under His Majeſty, upon any Acount whatſoever opreſs thee; His Majeſties Propper Courts can Right thee?
<pb facs="tcp:43472:9"/>Are the Judges thereof Parties concerned in point of Intereſt to favour thy Opreſſors and wrong thee, or do the Judges, or ſuch as the King intruſts to do thee Juſtice, deny or neglect to do their duty; thou haſt a juſt and wiſe King to apply unto, whoſe Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Prerogative is the moſt eſſential part of the Law: <hi>It is,</hi> ſaith a Learned Judge, <hi>A Sanctuary for the opreſſed to fly unto, a Fortreſs to the weak to retire unto, and a Curb to the inſolent.</hi> So that thou mayeſt depend on Juſtice at His Majeſties hands, becauſe His Majeſty can do no wrong; But the wiſdom of the Law knows, that His Majeſty ſees with others Eyes, and hears with others Ears, and acts with others Hands; and that they may be gulty of abuſing and wronging thee: Therefore the Law inflicts ſevere Puniſhment on ſuch in Authority under His Majeſty, as deceive His Majeſty by ill Advice, or do, or ſuffer any thing to be done againſt the Honour and Intereſt of His Majeſty, and his People; and His Majeſty may, when he thinks ſit, Sit in Perſon and ſee Juſtice done to any of his opreſſed or injured Subjects, for His Majeſty is Supream Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> and none is to depart his Courts without relief: And had His Majeſty time and leaſure to make one or two Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of Perſons exemplarily puniſhed for breach of Oath and Duty, it would eaſe His Majeſty of much trouble, and make His Majeſties Reign Glorious. Doth not the King underſtand the Laws, and will not his Councel adviſe him right; thou haſt thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives in <hi>Parliament,</hi> to make thy Caſe and Condition known to the King? Are thy Friends to Juſtice, out-voted by Parties intreſſed to favour thy Opreſſors and wrong thee? Thou haſt frequent <hi>Parliaments</hi> to apply unto, Art thou affraid the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43472:9"/>will chuſe the ſame Members? Every body knows that old Brooms being ſtumpy and ſtubborn, will ſcratch and leave Filth &amp; Rubbiſh in Holes and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes, where new Brooms, being buſhy and pliant, will ſweep clean: However, thou may do well to give thy Fellow Electors to underſtand, That the Law allows not Parties intereſted to be either Judges or Jury-men, and that under Sherffs are not allowed by Law to be in Office above a Year at a time; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Law preſumes, new Shereffs are not ſo Crafty as the old, nor will be guilty of their Tricks and Fallacys: And it may be believed, that it is as requiſite for none but indifferent Perſons to have Votes in the High Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> as to have indifferent Judges and Jury-men in the Inferior <hi>Courts,</hi> and that new Members to repreſent the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, may be as neceſſary as new Sherriffs in every County; let the People know the particulars of thy Caſe, and how thou art Oppreſſed, and by whom, and for what, and thou mayeſt happily prevail with them to chuſe ſuch to repreſent them and thee as live among them, and do all the Neighbourly good Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they can. For the People of <hi>England</hi> are naturally Stout, Generous, and lovers of Juſtice, and will do all things that may ſuit with the Honour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of their King and Country; and though Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Wars, Plots and Conſpiraces, have depraved their natural Tempers and Diſpoſitions: Yet in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of time they will be reclaimed, and thou mayeſt be ſucceſsful: Thou knoweſt that the unjuſt Judge in the Parable, who neither feared God nor reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced Man, was wrought upon by the importunate Widow to do her Juſtice, <hi>Gutta Cavit Lapidem non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi ſed ſepe Gadendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:43472:10"/>
            <p>For the ſupply of good Men to ſerve the King in Church and State, I humbly propoſe;</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That none (for the time to come) may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Holy Orders, until he hath taken his degree of <hi>Batchelour</hi> of <hi>Arts,</hi> in one of the two Univerſities of <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That when a Biſhoprick, or Benefice is vacant; the King or the Patron in whoſe gift the Benefice is, may give notice to the <hi>Chancellour</hi> or <hi>Vice-Chancellour</hi> of the reſpective Univerſities of the Vacancy: And the two Univerſities may in an Orderly and Regular way, as they chuſe Members to repreſent them in <hi>Parliament,</hi> proceed to Elect, in each Univerſity, a fit Perſon to ſupply the Vacancy: And the King or the Patron may divide by Lots, which of the Perſons ſo Elected and Recommended, ſhall be Inſtituted and Induced, to avoid diſobliging any body; becauſe <hi>Lots cauſeth Contention to Ceaſe, and parteth-between the Mighty,</hi> Prov. 8. ver. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> That all ſmall Livings may be Augmented and made ſufficient Maintanance, and Subſiſtance for the Incumbent.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> That all manner of great and ſmall <hi>Tyths,</hi> as ſoon as Benefices be vacant, be ſold to the beſt Advantage by fit Perſons to be appointed by His Majeſty in the vacancy for that purpoſe; and that all Sums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, raiſed by the Sale thereof, be laid out in Land that the Incumbant may be free from looking after, and gathring in the <hi>Tyths,</hi> whereby all occaſion of differences and diſputes between <hi>Parſons</hi> and <hi>Pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners</hi> upon Accompt of <hi>Tyths</hi> may be avoided.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> That ſo much as may be adjudged requiſite to be taken off, or away from great Livings, may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to and for the Augmentation of ſmall ones;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43472:10"/>or that the Augmentation be made by a general Tax, or that the firſt years Profits of Temporal Offices when they become void, as well as the firſt Fruits of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Livings, when vacant, be made a Revenue and applyed to that uſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> That no Perſon be permitted to hold, or enjoy two Livings.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> That the ſmall Salleries of all Offices in Church and State, may be Augmented, Inlarged, and made ſufficient; that the Officers need not be put to upon Shifts to pay themſelves at the Nations Coſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> That all Diſcoverers of Officers Undue Practiſes, and ſuch as make proper and advantageous Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals for the Redreſs of any Grievance ſit to be reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, may be duly encouraged; For, as Secretaries and Spials of State are allowed to bring in Bills for their diligence in the Inquiry and Diſcoveries of new Occurrences and Secrets in Forreign Eſtates: So if Encouragement be not given for home National Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, you ſhall never be advertiſed of many things moſt worthy to be known; Examples enough of this kind in all Flouriſhing States and Governments may be given to demonſtrate the neceſſity and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> That a Regeſtry may be kept of the Names of all Perſons doing good and publick ſervice, and that the Pooreſt ſort, may according to their Services and Qualifications be advanced to Offices as they become void, in the Firſt place; and the Richer ſort to be provided for afterward in like manner.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> That in caſe not any in the Regiſtry be Qualified for the Office vold, and if the Office be in the Kings Houſhold, Exciſe, Cuſtoms, or elſe where, and not in any of his Majeſties Courts of Law or Equity;
<pb facs="tcp:43472:11"/>and if two or more be Competitors for it, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty may for his own eaſe, appoint indifferent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be Tryers and Examiners of the Petitioners Qualifications? and if ſuch Tryers find two or more equally Qualified for it, the Preference may be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Lotts, becauſe 'tis morally impoſſible other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to Gratifie one of ſuch Petitioners, without diſobliging the reſt: And Perſons diſobliged are apt to be diſcontented and factious, and if Partiality be not avoided in beſtowing Offices, as well as Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, the Adminiſtration will be <hi>Male</hi> and Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Ad Infinitum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> That upon the Vacancy of a <hi>Judge, Attorney, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciter General,</hi> or other of the Kings Councel at Law, the <hi>Inns of Court</hi> may in every of their Societies Elect one fit to ſucceed; and his Majeſty may order Lotts to determine who ſhall ſucced.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> That when any Office in any of the Courts of Law or Equity fall void, the <hi>Inns of Court</hi> and <hi>Chancery</hi> may in every of their reſpective Societies, Elect a fit Perſon to ſupply the vacancy; and Lotts may in like manner decide which of the Perſons ſo elected ſhall Succeed the Officer Deceaſed or Removed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> That the <hi>Judges</hi> may have certain and ſufficient Salleries ſetled as the<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3 St. 4.20 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3 Chap.</note> Laws intended to ſupport the dignity of their Places, in Liew of all Contingent <hi>Fees, Profits</hi> and <hi>Perquiſites</hi> which now ariſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, as Suits and Proceedings multiply.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> That Suitors may not waiſt and conſume their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance by <hi>Fob Bills, Feigned Pleas, Writs of Error</hi> and the like, for delay, or to Protract time, which be expenſive and troubleſome to <hi>Plaintiffs</hi> and <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants;</hi> the <hi>Judges</hi> may be impowered to allow ſuch time for the eaſe and benefit of Suitors, as may be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43472:11"/>obtained by expenſive Shifts, Tricks, and Falacies.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> That no Perſon, unable to pay or ſatisfy his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors their whole Debts, may be kept in Priſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs every Creditor, at whoſe Suit the <hi>Defendant</hi> is deteyned, do pay every week the Sum of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> to and for the <hi>Defendants</hi> Maintenance and Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; becauſe Priſons deſtroy Debtors willing, but unable to Pay their whole Debts, and put them out of all Capacity to be ſerviceable to themſelves and others, whereby their <hi>Wives</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> become Burthenſome to the Pariſhes they Live in: As for the Debtors Real and Perſonal Eſtates, they may be Subject and Lyable to be Seized and Diſtributed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually among all the real Creditors; But if a Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor hath no Eſtate but what is imployed in his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Trade, or in ſome Occupation or Lawful Courſe of Living, and doth out of the Product thereof pay to his Creditors what he can reaſonably ſpare (over and above his own <hi>Wife</hi> and <hi>Childrens</hi> Neceſſary and Competent Subſiſtence) Then the Creditors to take their Debts in proportion as the ſame can be raiſed: And the Debtors Eſtate, or Effects, ſo Imployed, to be exempted from all <hi>Seizures</hi> and <hi>Executions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> That the <hi>Attorney</hi> and <hi>Solliciter-General,</hi> and every other of the Kings <hi>Councel</hi> at Law, may be allowed certain and ſufficient <hi>Sallarys</hi> to Plead and Maintain <hi>Actions,</hi> populer <hi>Informations</hi> and <hi>Pleas</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> Gratis; and may be Prohibited to Practice and take any <hi>Fee</hi> in Cauſes between Party and Party, and may be ſet at work to Correct the Errors and Miſtakes in our Law Books, and Explain doubtful Points, and expunge ſuch things as too often miſguide young <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,</hi> to their <hi>Clyents</hi> great loſs and damage.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43472:12"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> That all <hi>Grants,</hi> or <hi>Letters Pattents</hi> of <hi>Crown</hi>-Lands, not already Confirmed by <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> may now be Confirmed, becauſe the ſame are diſperſed and got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into the hands of many Perſons by mean <hi>Conveyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Statutes, Judgments, Extents,</hi> &amp;c. and many of the Grantees and Venders are unable, in Caſe the ſame be reſtored to the Crown to repay the Purchaſe-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or make or give any Satisfaction to the Purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers thereof: And the dread of Acts of Reſumption makes the Poſſeſſors of ſuch Land againſt their own Inclinations, Chuſe ſuch to repreſent them in <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament</hi> as be the Venders, or their Heirs, or intereſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to oppoſe Acts of Reſumption. And their Fears and Jealouſies, occaſions Factions and Diſturbance.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> That Elections of Members to ſerve in Parliament, may be ſo ſettled by Ballat or Boxes, that Electors may not be known for whom they Vote or give their Voices; becauſe many chuſe their Oppreſſors (as the <hi>Indians</hi> Worſhip the <hi>Devil</hi>) that they may not hurt them; and the fewds and differences between Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and near Relations upon accompt of Elections are wofully experienced in many places.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Many Perſons have loſt, or may looſe their Lives or Eſtates, or both, by doing good and Publick Services, and their Widdows or Children may not be capable of Offices; and the Government is ſo much in Debt, that the King cannot reward them with Penſions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The King is ſo Juſt to his Parliaments, That he will not give Pentions out of any Branch of his Revenue Appropriated to the War, or to pay debts: And if the Branches not Appropriated, be not ſuffici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Services, the People will readily Pay any Tax or Impoſition to Reward good Services Liberally;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43472:12"/>becauſe it is for the Honour and Intereſt of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo to do.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Many Advowſons and Benefices are the Inheritance of private Patrons, whoſe Right of Preſcription can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be taken away, without invading their Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Records are Living Witneſſes, Teſtifying, That Lands, Benefices and Offices, were in the Gift and Diſpoſition of the Crown, when <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror</hi> obliged his true and faithful Friends and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants therewith: And we read not of any privy Conſpiracy or Rebellion againſt any of his Succeſſors until thoſe Favours were bought and ſold; and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſers ſo abuſed both Crown and People, That moſt Dependants on the Crown, were under the ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Ill Officers and Guardians, who Bought and Sold young Heirs being Wards, and made few or none of them fit for the Service of their King or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
            <p>Private Patrons, abuſing their Truſt, occaſioned Laws to be made againſt <hi>Simony,</hi> and ſuch as abuſed their Truſt by Selling Offices under the King, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned the Laws againſt buying and ſelling Offices and Places of Truſt; and ill Officers and Guardians op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing Wards, made Tenures and Services in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite be turned into free and common Soccage: And with humble ſubmiſſion, all thoſe Laws will be difficient until ſome way be found out, that it may not be in the power of any in Authority under the King, or by a derivative Power, to make ill Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or Officers in Church or State.</p>
            <p>Private Patrons can make no manner of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of their Preſentations, without diſpencing with the Laws againſt <hi>SIMONY:</hi> And though
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43472:13"/>ſuch as influence their younger Sons to be Parſons, and give or procure them Benifices in liew of their Portions, may be winked at by ſuch as are guilty of diſpencing with the Laws againſt Buying and Selling places of Truſt: Yet the People of <hi>England</hi> who love Juſtice, and the Laws that provide againſt any to be advanced; to Offices of Truſt, for Money, Brocage, Favour or Affection, certainly intended that the Truſt for the cure of Souls ſhould not be Committed to <hi>Siſmaticks,</hi> or ſuch as will either Buy or Sell their Truſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 'Tis believed that the Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and Officers, who are Expoſitors and Executioners of the Law, Buy and Sell Offices and Places of Truſt; And that others do the like by their Example.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> He that Buyes will Sell,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gna Charta <hi>5</hi> Hen. <hi>3.</hi> Chap. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> but the Law provides, That Juſtice ſhall not be Sold, Delayed, or Denied to any; That,<note n="a" place="margin">2 Hen. 6. <hi>C.</hi> 10.12 Rich 2. <hi>Chap</hi> 2.</note> not any Perſon ſhall be advanced to Offices for Money, Brocage, Favour or Affection, but upon Merit: That<note n="b" place="margin">5 &amp; 6. Edw. 6. <hi>Chap</hi> 16.</note> he who ſells an Office, ſhall Forfeit his Eſtate therein, and he that buys, ſhall be diſabled to hold it: And<note n="c" place="margin">Peti ion of Rights; <hi>Car. 1</hi>
               </note> Every perſon is Sworn to ſerve the King, according to the Laws and Statutes of the Realm.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="d" place="margin">18 Edw. 3 <hi>S.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 20 Edw. 3. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.</note> It is alſo adjudged Bribery for any in Judicial place to take Money, Fee, Gift, or ought of value of any private perſon: And<note n="e" place="margin">Inſt. 3 <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o.</hi> 145.148. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ons <hi>Caſe</hi> Inſt. 1 <hi>Part Fo.</hi> 134.</note> upon the Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one that ſold an Office, to loſe his Eſtate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and the Purchaſer was adjudged diſabled to hold it, whereupon it was granted to a third-Perſon for life.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1 H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 4 <hi>C</hi> 6. Inſt 1 Part Fo. 1.</note> It is alſo provided, That ſuch Perſons as challenge any Office or other thing of value by Grant, without expreſs Mention of the name and value, ſhall he puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43472:13"/>for Deceit: And the Grants ſhall be void. And not any inferiour Office by expreſs name, being mentioned in any Grant, Commiſſions, or Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents to any of the Judges, or great Officers, they have not any Right or Title thereto.</p>
            <p>Offices are Propper Rewards for good Services,<note place="margin">1 Hen. 4 Ca. Inſt 4 <hi>Part Fo.</hi> 56.</note> It was therefore provided, That ſuch as had been Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the Publick ſhall be rewarded with Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Kings Gift: And Offices are incident to the Adminiſtration, and Originally inſtituted to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it; and the Adminiſtration is inſeparably Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Anexed to the Crown: Conſequently Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces incident thereto, are the Inheritance of the Crown, and by force of the Stat. 5 and 6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6 Chap. 16. The King may make a Revenue thereof.</p>
            <p>The many Preſidents upon Record ſhew, That ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther former Kings underſtood their own Right to Grant Offices,<note place="margin">Vide the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co d in the <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> and <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s Chappel.</hi>
               </note> or had knowing and honeſt Miniſters for the Office of Prothonotary, Regiſter, Clark of the Crown, Incorporation of the Six Cleks, Curſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and others in <hi>Chancery;</hi> The <hi>Cuſtos Brevium,</hi> Clerk of the Crown, Chief Clerk or Prothonotary, and others in the <hi>Kings-Bench:</hi> The <hi>Cuſtos Breveum</hi> Chyrographer Clerk of the <hi>Treaſury,</hi> and others in the <hi>Common-Pleas:</hi> The Treaſurer, Remembrancer, Clerk of the Pipe, and others in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> were (and moſt of them are now) Granted and Enjoyed by Letters Patents, <hi>Pari ratione,</hi> His Majeſty may Grant all other Offices of like nature and Tenure.</p>
            <p>When any Miniſter under Colour of his Office,<note place="margin">Dyer 127.</note> Challenged the right of Granting ſome of the ſaid Offices, and the diſpute between them and the King about the Right, came to be farely debated; It was Adjudged for the Kng,<note place="margin">Hob <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 46.</note> by reaſon ſuch Acts of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:43472:14"/>as Impowered the Miniſters to do what the King had right to do, ſhall not barr or take away the King's Right: But the ſame remain full and perfect, becauſe ſuch Acts were intended to eaſe the King of Labour, not to deprive him of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Prerogative<note n="*" place="margin">Inſt. 1. <hi>Part Fo.</hi> 119. 2 <hi>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 436.</note> which is a moſt eſſential part of the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Acts of <hi>Parliament,</hi> wherein the King is not named<note n="a" place="margin">Inſt. 1. <hi>Part Fo</hi> 43. Cook 11 <hi>Rep.</hi> Mag. Coll. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe.</hi>
               </note> ſhall not bart or take away the Kings right, and that General words in <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament Grants, Uſe, Cuſtom,</hi> or <hi>Preſcription,</hi> ſhall not deveſt the <hi>Crown</hi> of any thing originally, and of right belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it.</p>
            <p>That not any can preſcribe to the Temperaltys of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. <hi>2.</hi> Part Fo. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> becauſe they are incident to the Perſon of the King, as Patron and Protector of the Church; and<note n="b" place="margin">Ibid. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Part Fo.</hi> 117.</note> all Courts of Juſtice are the Kings, as Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrator of Juſtice: And Offices incident to his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, being inſeparably United and Annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Imperial Crown, cannot be ſevered from it<note n="c" place="margin">Hob. <hi>Rep.</hi> 261.</note> but by ſpecial <hi>Grant</hi> or <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament:</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Idem. 22<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.342.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the People of <hi>England</hi> have an Intereſt in the Rites of the Crown.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ibid. 347.</note> Where the Crown hath a Right it cannot looſe it, and not any thing ſhall paſs out of the Crown but by ſpecial Grant; neither ſhall Officers Compact Defeat the Crown: And not any inferiour Office was ever granted by name to any Miniſter or Judge, becauſe<note n="f" place="margin">I ſt. 4. <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Fo.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>00. Hob. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>55.</note> by the Ancient Rule in Law, not any is to enjoy two Offices and Rules in Law, cannot be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken without doing abuſe and deceit to the King; and<note n="g" place="margin">13. Edw. 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 44.</note> Judges are Charged upon Faith and Oath to Puniſh; but if they in their own right grant Offices, they are Puniſhable when their Officers offend, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43472:14"/>it's againſt a Rule in Law, for any to be Judge and Party.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. Granted the diſpoſition of Fellons Goods to his <hi>Almoner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cook <hi>Rep.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton woods <hi>Caſe.</hi>
               </note> and without reciting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking the ſame, did grant divers Fellons Goods to one <hi>Hales;</hi> and the <hi>Almoner</hi> diſputed his right, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Stat.</hi> 6 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Cap. 15. Saith all after Grants not reciting and revoking the former, ſhall be void, yet the latter grant to <hi>Hales</hi> was Adjuged good againſt the <hi>Almoner;</hi> becauſe he was only a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in Truſt for the King: And great Officers are no other, neither have they ſuch expreſs Grants of the diſpoſition of Inferiour Offices, as the <hi>Almoner</hi> had of Fellons Goods.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Edward</hi> 1ſt. Granted the Office of Maſter of the <hi>Rolls</hi> to one for life,<note place="margin">Inſt 3. <hi>Part Fo.</hi> 95.96. 9 Edw. 4 <hi>Fo.</hi> 6, 7.18 Edw. 4. <hi>Fo.</hi> 7. Dyer 176 Hob. <hi>Rep.</hi> 153.</note> and ſetled the diſpoſition to be ever after in the gift of the <hi>Chancellour</hi> or <hi>Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of the Great Seal for the time being; yet it was adjudged when the Office of the Maſter of the <hi>Rolls</hi> was void, to be ſtill in the Kings gift, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſettlement: And many other Offices when their right of Granting was diſputed, were adjudged to be in the Kings Gift.</p>
            <p>In Caſe the Judges had a right, as they pretend, it muſt neceſſarily terminate upon their own Death or Removal; yet they preſume to grant Eſtates in Offices to others, for one, two, or more Lives, which Grants are Illegal, being againſt a Rule in Law, that ſaith, <hi>None ſhall transfer a greater Eſtate then he hath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Law ever looked upon the Injurious Acts of Perſons in Office, to be worſe then Robbing on the High way; Becauſe a Theif can take but what thou carrieſt about thee, but wreſting the Law or execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it Partially, may deſtroy Men and their Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43472:15"/>All Laws are to be Expounded moſt Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to make them anſwer their true End,<note place="margin">Plow. <hi>Com.</hi> 563. Dyer 231.313. Brook 77. Inſt. 1 <hi>Part</hi> 381. Co. <hi>Rep.</hi> Alton woods <hi>Caſe.</hi> Heydens <hi>Caſe.</hi>
               </note> for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the Evils they intend to remedy; and the Conſtruction which the Judges make of the proviſo in the <hi>Stat.</hi> 5 and 6 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. Chap. 16. for them to ſell in repugnant to the Laws againſt Buying and Selling Offices; neither doth that proviſo repeal the <hi>Stat.</hi> 12. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. Cap. 2. So that the Judges can but do as they might have done, that is to ſay, for the Kings Eaſe, or untill his Pleaſure be ſignified to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; they may ſupply Offices void, ſo that there be no failer for want of a propper and ſit Perſon in the Execution of the Law: And the Kings of <hi>England</hi> had no reaſon to trouble themſelves with Offices upon the firſt Erection, by reaſon they were few and ſmall, and of little value, but now they are many and of great value, and would raiſe a great Revenue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſobliging any body: For when an Office is void, and in the Kings gift, any man will be glad of the Moity of the Profits to live on, and to pay the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Moiety to the King for two Years, and to have the whole after the Expiration thereof, without pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing out of his own Pocket, becauſe then the Officer will not be put upon ſhifts to raiſe his Purchaſe-Money, or reimburſe himſelf, as too many have been of Late years. And if Perſons that do good Service, be releaſed from paying their firſt years Profits, the Obligation or Indearment will be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> In Caſe Offices be in the Kings Gift, why ſhould you propoſe the ſame to be Elective by Societys, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I Propoſe none to be Elective by Societys, but in Caſe where there is not a Perſon in the Regiſtry of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43472:15"/>good Services, Qualified for the Office void, and that will make all his Majeſty's Subjects ſtrive to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel each other in Dutiful and Loyal Services, and qualifie themſelves for good Offices and Imployments; were Perſons Qualifications written in their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, there needed no Tryers or Examiners, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Report or Recommendation, who are fit, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: But ſeeing his Majeſty deſires nothing, but to be well ſerved, and have his own and his Peoples buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs well and carefully done. And Tryers, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminers, and Societies, where Perſons have not done any ſignal Service to recommend them, may reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably be believed to be more indifferent and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in their Reports and Recommendations, than pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſons, who may be ſuſpected to make it their buſineſs, for Money, Brocage, Favour or Affection, to Procure Offices; and ſeeing it is hard to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh Generous Noble Souls, from ſuch as are Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinary, and Sell their Prince's Favours: It is, as I conceive, the Intereſt of a Prince to prevent Evils which may be ſecretly Tranſacted, againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Intereſt of His Majeſty and His People: whoſe Intereſt being united, cannot be ſevered; for that Reaſon, whenever a Private Intereſt comes in Competition with a Publick Benefit or Advantage, Judgment is to be given, <hi>Pro Communi utilitate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis &amp; Populi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Records ſhew, that King <hi>James</hi> the 1ſt. had not Reigned above Three Years, before the moſt Horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Gun-Powder-Treaſon Plot</hi> was Ripe, and ready to be put in Execution, at a time when the People were much Diſſatisfied and Diſcontented with Favorites, Monopolizing old, and Erecting new Offices of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; whereupon his Majeſty Iſſued out his <hi>Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43472:16"/>to put a ſtop to all further Suit to be made to him for new Offices; and Judgment was given againſt ſome that had Bought and Sold Offices, to Loſe both Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Office: And had the Diſpoſition of Offices been ſo Setled, that it had not been in the power of Favourites to have over-ballanced the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Ill Men, <hi>Wards</hi> and their Eſtates had not been made a Prey to Ill Officers and <hi>Guardians,</hi> which occaſioned the Murder of his Son, and the Exile of his Grand-children. And had not the Favourites of King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> diſcontented the People, by neglecting ſuch as had Loſt all by their Duty and Loyalty, and over-ballanced the Adminiſtration with ſuch as were glutted with the Spoil and Pillage of the Crown and People: <hi>England</hi> might happily have Flouriſhed in his Reign, but the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> you know are very Rich and Cunning, and they, the <hi>French</hi> King, and the <hi>Devil</hi> their Maſter, ever took care to diſoblige ſuch moſt as had done their King and Country the beſt Service; becauſe their Complaints lie heavy upon the Shoulders of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and Friends diſobliged, that will be <hi>Male-Contents</hi> and Diſaffected, are the worſt of Enemies. It would fill a Volume to particularize how and which way they divided our Councils in the late Reigns, and ſowed Strife and Debate among their late Majeſties Houſhold, Servants and Favourites, and ſet up one Party or Faction, to pull down ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and made one Party jealous of another, and both of the King, and the King of them; and what Aid and Aſiſtance was given to the Party or Faction that Debauched or Diſcontented the People moſt, and Ripened them for Rebellion; and how the Crown was Stript of its Ancient <hi>Regalia's</hi> and <hi>Inheritance,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:43472:16"/>and how the ſame were Sold by the Grantees, and diſperſed into many private hands, that when the Crown ſtood moſt in need of Aids and Supplies, there might be Squabbling about Acts of <hi>Reſumption,</hi> mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpending the Publick-Treaſure, and what not.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Doth not this Popular way of Electing and make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Clergy-men and Officers, put the Staff of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of the King's hand?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> There is a Law already in Force againſt Abuſes in Election of <hi>Schollars</hi> and Preſentation to Benefices; And you may remember His Majeſty, upon his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of the Adminiſttation, deſired the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to Name Officers; becauſe his Majeſty had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of few Perſons, or their Services, and his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty looked upon the Repreſentatives of his People to be moſt knowing and impartial: And undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly had they Recommended, they would not have neglected any that had done any Generous Service for the Crown and People.</p>
            <p>You have ſeldom any Benefice or Office of Value becomes void, but ſeveral be Competitors for it, and every one prevails with ſome to be his Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor; and it is Morally impoſſible to gratifie one, but the reſt will be apt to diſ-relliſh their diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Signall Service and Societies, Electing and Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending Perſons and Lots deciding the Preferrence of the Perſons Elected and Recomended, will diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige no body, but a few private Patrons, that would influence their younger Sons to be Parſons, to give or procure them Benefices in Liew of their Portions; and ſuch as diſpence with the Laws againſt <hi>Simony,</hi> and Buying and Selling Offic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, are but a handful of Men gratified, to the vaſt numbers of His Majeſty's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb facs="tcp:43472:17"/>will be indeared by a right diſpoſition of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Offices.</p>
            <p>This Method Propoſed, will certainly eaſe the King of much Trouble, and leave no room for his Majeſty's Enemies to blame His Majeſty; 'Tis not Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining, Naming, or Making Officers, but their Rewards or Puniſhments well placed, wherein the Staff of Government reſts: And while His Majeſty hath Full and Sole Power to Reward ſuch Liberally as are found True and Truſty, and to Remove and Puniſh ſuch as are found Falſe and Treacherous, His Majeſty may keep the Hearts of his People Firm and Fixt, which Commands their Hands and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: And ſuch as Mis-behave themſelves, will then have no Parties or Factions of their own Making, in Church or State, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly unto.</p>
            <p>You know the People upon His Majeſty's Acceſs to the Crown, were as Debauched as the <hi>Devil,</hi> the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King, in the late Reigns, could make them; yet being true to their Common Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and ſtedfaſtly believing His Majeſty would be ſo, they planted the Crown upon his Sacred Head, and his Majeſty hath moſt intirely followed the Advice and Counſels of his <hi>Parliament,</hi> to the great Joy and Satisfaction of all good <hi>Protestants;</hi> and never Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple gave greater demonſtration of Love and Duty to a Prince, than the People of theſe his Majeſty's Realms and Dominions have done to his Majeſty; and long may their Mutual Love and Affection continue and increaſe, are the hearty Deſires of all that truly wiſh the Peace and Safety of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and other his Majeſty's Dominions.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:43472:17"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Are not many private Patrons, and ſuch as have or claim the Preſentations of Benefices, and Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Offices, <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Mannors,</hi> and Men of Power and Intereſt, to Influence <hi>Boroughs</hi> to Elect them: And have not <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> equal Voices with Knights of <hi>Shires,</hi> then how can theſe Propoſals take effect?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>
               </label> The People know that the Commons of <hi>England</hi> in Parliament aſſembled, are the Grand Inqueſt of the Nation, and that their Laws expreſs their Averſion to every thing that ſmells of Partiality or Private Intereſt; and will any Man of Senſe omit his Challenge of an Array or Pannel, or not take Exception to any returned upon a Jury, to give Verdict of a thing in Queſtion concerns him: And will Men of Underſtanding chuſe ſuch to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them in Parliament; as be Parties Intereſted to oppoſe any thing that is fit to be done for the Common Good and Benefit of the Crown and People.</p>
            <p>You know the Advancement of ſuch as ſignalize themſelves by their Services, will be, without all doubt, well liked by every body; and ſuch as are not ſignalized by Services, cannot be Advanced, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Report of ſome body; if of particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, their Report or Recommendation may be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to be Partial; ſo that you may believe private Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons and Office-Jobbers will not be able, by all their Artifices, to delude the generality of the People, who heartily deſire and wiſh that the Clergy were had in due Reverence and Eſteem; that none but Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Worthy and Meet, may be Advanced to Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, Benefices, and Offices; and that ſuch as have good Eſtates, and Work enough to Husband and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
<pb facs="tcp:43472:18"/>the ſame well, were not put into Offices of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, to keep younger Sons of Parents, well deſcended, out of ſuch Imployments as they are fitly Qualified for, and have Time and Leiſure to be more Service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in: That all Loyal and Dutiful Services were Liberally Rewarded; That all under any Oppreſſion for diſcharge of Oath and Duty, were Relieved, and due Care taken of the Pooreſt of them in the Firſt Place.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But Boroughs, wherein are few Inhabitants, will hardly conſider ought but their own private In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Some may be Stupified until they be Disfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed: The People of <hi>England</hi> are not ſo Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and Illiterate, as they were when the Duke of <hi>Cornwall</hi> multiplied Burgeſſes, nor when the Abby-Lands, and the Ancient Rights, Prerogative and Authorities of Juſtice,<note place="margin">27 Hen. 8. Cap. 24.</note> were reſcued out of the hands of the Pope and his Petty Tyrants.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> King <hi>Hen.</hi> the 8th. was not involved in War, and Eſpouſed the Cauſe, and gave his People to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his and their Common Intereſt; but the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſo Imbroyled with Wars Abroad, Factions, Plots and Conſpiracies at Home, that his Majeſty wants Leiſure to Conſider the many Inconveniencies that attend Him and his People, by not having the Defects of the Laws againſt <hi>Simony</hi> (and Buying and Selling Offices) ſupplied; and you know ſeveral in Authority under <hi>Hen.</hi> the 8th. were as Active as the King, to make the People ſenſible of their own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43472:18"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I Anſwer, The People are not ſo Ignorant and Illiterate at this time, but now all that are not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blind, ſee which ſide their <hi>Bread</hi> is <hi>Butter'd</hi> on: 'Tis thy Duty and mine, in our Private and Publick Devotions, to Pray for the King, and all that are put in Authority under him, that they may truly and indifferently Miniſter Juſtice and Maintain Truth; and we beſt Expreſs our Chriſtian Duties, when we in our particular Callings, Profeſſions and Trades, be Serviceable Members of the State, as well as of the Church.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the King wants time to read, but His Majeſty hath many Honourable and Worthy Perſons in Authority under Him, that have Leiſure enough, and what they conceive fit to be done for His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Service, they will undoubtedly Adviſe and Counſel His Majeſty for the Beſt. All that Truly Love and Honour His Majeſty, and heartily Deſire and Wiſh the Proſperity of Him and His People, are for Extirpating ſuch things as make Parties and Factions in Church and State. And ſeeing 'tis uſual to deſcribe ſuch Criminals as go by different Names, and skulk to avoid Juſtice, I will according to the beſt of my Skill, diſcover a Symoniacal Parſon, and an Office-Jobber, that they may be known and apprehended.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:43472:19"/>
            <p>
               <label>The Character of a Parſon guilty of Symony.</label> He may be known by the extraordinary Pains he takes a little before he is to be examined by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or his Official; a poor Felon who has the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his Clergy, that can neither Write nor Read, is not harder put to his Shifts to learn his Neck-verſe by Rote, than a Parſon guilty of Symony is to fit himſelf for his Examination: And as ſoon as inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and inducted, his whole Study and Buſineſs is, how to make moſt of his Benefice: And after that he is ſo taken up with Attending Courts of Juſtice, in Suits between him and his Pariſhoners, that he has much to do to eſcape the Penalties of the Law againſt Non-reſidency: When Overtures of Peace are made, he ſaith, Let the Law decide it, that his Succeſſors may not blame him: And never makes any Agreement upon his own Terms, without a <hi>Salvo jure</hi> to his Succeſſors, That they may place him in the Liſt of their Benefactors: When he ſees Complaint will be made of him to the Ordinary or Biſhop at his Viſitation, he has recourſe to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, and by Contrivance between his Patron and him, the Matter is huſh'd up if poſſible; but in caſe it be not, their buſineſs is, by their Parties and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to repreſent the Complaints, Schiſmatical Factions, and what not: His Flock are ever Bleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for another Sheepherd, as Lambs for want of their Dams; and if they are not to be found in their Neighbouring Sheepherd's Fold, they are ſtray'd fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and loſt.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:43472:19"/>
            <p>
               <label>The Character of an Office-Jobber.</label> He is of a Religion uppermoſt, a moſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd Temporizer; his Ambition hates to ſee any of his poor and beggarly Kindred, or to do any thing for them, until he hath robed them with Honour, Offices, and what not, at the Nations and Poor Petitioners Coſt; or he is ſo Covetous, that he cares not what he gets, or how he gets, ſo he can but get and heap up Riches. He is always Poor, crying, <hi>Give, Give,</hi> but never ſatisfied with what is given. He will not ſerve any but in Matters wherein he can ſerve or gratifie himſelf; as little Credit is to be given to his Oaths, as to Whores Vows: He is true to no Government, yet Zealous in Appearance to ſerve every Government; but Water-man-like, Looks one way and Rows another. He hates all Loyal Services, which repreſent any worthy of a Liberal Reward; Eſpecially ſuch as are Poor and cannot purchaſe it. He is never with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Jackhall</hi> to Forrage for him: When he meets a Man of Merit, he cries Shame no Proviſion is made for him; and when his Back is turned, he redicules him for a Fool, that ſerves his King and Country to the Prejudice of himſelf: For publick Buſineſs he accounts every bodies Work, and every bodies Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, to be no bodies in particular: But the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Work of ſuch as can ſerve Turns, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at every Turn: His common Diſcourſe is, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Liberty and Property; But feeds ſo greedily on Pippins and Pigg ſtuffed with Guinea's, that he is Sloathful and Unactive to do his King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try any manner of Service: His Complements are,
<pb facs="tcp:43472:20"/>
               <hi>I am but one, and I will ſerve you if I can, or come again to-morrow and your Buſineſs ſhall certainly be done:</hi> And when you come in Expectation thereof, it is ſtill to-morrow; And at laſt when he had gratified whom he thinks fit, he tells you, He is Sorry he cannot Serve you: And if your Buſineſs happens to be done againſt his Will, he tells you how Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable he hath been to you: And that there is no Fee eſtabliſhed for his extraordinary Care, Pains, and Expedition, but will take what you give him: In plain Terms, Nothing but weighty Preſents, are weighty Reaſons, can work him into a Frame or Diſpoſition to do you a Juſt Favour, or Friendly Office; by vertue of <hi>Hocus Pocus Colore Officii,</hi> he can Drein your Purſes, Afflict your Mind and Body; and do it ſo inſenſibly, that you may accuſe him, but cannot recover any Satisfaction for the Loſs and Damage you ſuſtain. You may know him by the great number of Petitioners wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at his Gate for Recommendations or Reports of their Services; and when his Tricking is found out, and he is likely to fall under His Majeſty's Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, he of himſelf fairly acquits all Publick Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, and becomes a Country-Gentleman, and there lives Great among his Neighbours, and treats them with all imaginable Courteſie and Civility, until they forget what manner of Man he was: And in proceſs of Time ſets up to be choſen a Member of Parliament: And if the People Elect him, he Acts his part like a Mountebank, to Gull the World with inſipid Drugs and Medicines, of the Jeſuits and <hi>French King's</hi> Compoſing. And ſearch the Books and Files of his Receipts and Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and his Coffers, and you will find who
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43472:20"/>compoſed his Medicines and <hi>Lewis d'Ores</hi> good Store.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> In caſe Symoniacal Parſons, and Office-Jobbers, be ſuch Dangerous Enemies to the King and his People, Were it not better to have a ſtrict Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny preſently? For 'tis certain ſuch as have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed Benefices and Offices with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> or <hi>French King's Money,</hi> will ſerve their Turns; and ſuch as have purchaſed with their own Money, will be upon the Spurs to re-imburſe themſelves; and both will act all for their own private Gain and Profit; but as little as may be for the true Honour and Intereſt of their King and Country: And the Propoſals aforeſaid are only for the time to come. Now admit an Office of Truſt ſhould become void, and a Worthy Good Man ſhould ſucceed therein as propoſed, if the Majority of Men in Office be Good, he may do a great deal of Good: But in caſe the Majority be ſuch as came in by Money, Brocage, Favour or Affection; the Good will be but like a piece of New Cloth ſet upon an Old Garment, or New Wine put into Old Bottles; for the Bandittee of Office Jobbers will make all honeſt Men very uneaſie, who cannot wink at or diſpenſe with ſuch things as the Bandittee allow to be Good and Practicable.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I ſuppoſe the Government hath paid a great deal for the Learning of the moſt Ignorant Perſons in Office; and if any of them do not underſtand their proper Work and Buſineſs at this time of day, they deſerve to be kick'd out of Imployment; and the Cunning will give over all their Tricks and Falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,
<pb facs="tcp:43472:21"/>when the Gift or Diſpoſition of Offices is ſettled as propoſed, becauſe they cannot make Friends or Parties with Offices in their Gift or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation as they have done: And ſuch as have done Good Service, are propoſed to be taken Care of; ſo that the future Settlement propoſed, will work a preſent Cure. But would the Lords-Juſtices, now in His Majeſty's Abſence, pleaſe to appoint ſpecial Commiſſioners to Examine and Enquire into the Behaviour and Qualifications of ſuch as be ſuſpected to misbehave themſelves, or to be Ignorant of the Work and Buſineſs properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to their Offices, undoubtedly upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of indifferent Commiſſioners ſo appointed, many and great Abuſes would be diſcovered, which the Government might think fit and neceſſary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to redreſs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Is it ſafe to have ſuch Enquiry made at this time?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I humbly Conceive, That it would oblige and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear the Generality of His Majeſty's Loving and Dutiful Subjects, and none will be diſobliged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, or Diſcontented at it, but Rotten or Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>green'd Members or Branches, which muſt either be Diſſected, or paired and ſcraped, that their Ruſt and Canker may not Corrupt the whole Body or Maſs of Government, or hinder it to Thrive and Flouriſh.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Would not this be better for Committees of the Two Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I humbly Conceive, That His Majeſty and His People are beſt ſerved and pleaſed, when Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43472:21"/>ring leaſt of Grievances; and the more Active Princes and Private Councils are, to find out and redreſs Abuſes in the Intervals of Parliament, the leſs Work will Parliaments have when they meet, and their Councils will be more Free and undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed: And if the Commiſſioners appointed be not True and Truſty, the King and His Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, or the Parliament, will find out their Roguery, for the Blot will be Hit ſome time or other, and then Woe be to ſuch, if any there be, who like the Chief Prieſts and Elders, have abuſed the Ears of Government.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Reader,</hi> I beg of thee to be like the Bee, that Sucks her Honey where the Spider gathers her Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: I know by woful Experience, that the beſt things ſaid and done, may, by Mercinary and ill Men, be wreſted to wrong Purpoſes. I do aſſure thee, if any ſo wreſt what I have done, or make ill Conſtructions thereof, it is their own Fault not mine: For I declare to thee in the Preſence of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, unto whom all Hearts be open, all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires known, and from whom no Secrets are hid, that I have no other End in publiſhing this to the World, but to Communicate ſuch things to all that truly Love and Honour His Majeſty, that they may improve my Talent for the Service of their King and Country. Was I under no Obligation of Oaths, Gratitude would oblige me to be as Serviceable as I may or can be to His Majeſty; But being under the Obligation of Old and New Oaths, to do my King and Country the beſt Service I can in my Calling and Profeſſion, I hope none that reads this, but will pardon my Infirmities. Do thou but read
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43472:22"/>the Petition which the Lords and Commons of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> in Parliament Aſſembled,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Car.</hi> 1.</note> preſented to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and thou wilt find their Prayer in the Concluſion is, <hi>That His Majeſty would be Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Pleaſed, for the further Comfort and Safety of his People, to declare His Royal Will and Pleaſure, That all Officers and Miniſters ſhall ſerve him according to the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, as they tender the Honour of His Majeſty, and the Proſperity of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> And were His now Majeſty ſo ſerved, there would be no Male-Contents, or Parties, or Factions, in Court or Country: Conſequently Plots and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies would be at an end; and in all Parts of His Majeſty's Realms and Dominions, the loud Acclamations of the People would be, <hi>O King, Live for Ever.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>UPON the Rumor and Report of a General Peace abroad, I did add this, Dear Countrymen, to let you ſee what will Unite and Settle us in Peace at Home, ſo that every Man may ſit and enjoy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf under his own Vine free and undiſturbed; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Generality of Free-holders and Free-men will not conſider their own Intereſt. It is certainly a great Diſparagement to Vertue and Learning it ſelf, That thoſe very things which only make Men uſeful in the World, ſhould incline them to leave it: This ought never to be allowed to Good Men, unleſs the Bad had the ſame Moderation, and were willing to follow them into the Wilderneſs: For if the Good Content to get out of Publick Imployments, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43472:22"/>live retiredly; and the Bad ſtrive to get into Publick Places of Truſt, the Affairs of Mankind are like to be in ſo ill a Poſture, that even Good Men themſelves will hardly be able to enjoy their very Retreats in Security.</p>
            <p>What (with humble Submiſſion) is more Injurious to the Government, than ſuch in Commiſſions of Peace, as have the Fines and Forfeitures of Perſons Convicted? What hinders the Increaſe of Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ſit Perſons to be Sea-men and Marriners, but Tenants and Farmers to Vice Admirals and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace, that under the Umbrage of Royalties of Fiſhing, Potch and Fiſh, and hinder ſuch to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Trade of Fiſhing in Times of Peace, as would be free to go to Sea, and ſerve his Majeſty, in Times of War? What puts Millers upon Grinding the Face of the Poor, by extorting unreaſonable Toll or Moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of them, But Lords of Royalties Letting their Mills to Farm at exceſſive Rent? What makes Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of Leets remiſs to remove Nuſances, But to have the ſame Preſented over and over again? What makes Stewards of Liberties, and under Sheriffs, Pack Juries, and be remiſs in their Turns or Leets, or the chief Duties of their Offices, But Diſpenſing with the Laws againſt Letting out their Bailywicks to Farm? In ſhort,<note place="margin">23 Hen. 6. Cap. 10.27 Hen. 8. Cap. 24.</note> What makes any in Office under the King, Guilty of undue Practices, But Patrons, Parſons, Judges, and others by their Example, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing with the Laws againſt Symony, and Buying and Selling Places of Truſt? Are not their Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Deſtructive to the Government? Have Good Men ought but Good Laws, and the due Execution thereof, to keep Ill Men within the Circle of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience? Are not Rewards the Golden Spur to Glory
<pb facs="tcp:43472:23"/>and all Noble Actions? Do not Rewards and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments miſplaced, make a Weak and Tottering State? Did not King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third,<note place="margin">15 Edw. 3.</note> as ſoon as he had opportunity, make void ſeveral Laws, to which his Conſent was not Free; but Diſſembled, to eſchew ſome Eminent Dangers he foreſaw might enſue, by his denying the ſame at that time: And was not the late Impoſition of <hi>Waterborne</hi> Coals taken off, when the Poor, for want of Firing, deſtroyed and burned their Neighbours Pales and Hedges. And now having done my Duty, in giving my Brethren to underſtand their Grievances, and making Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals for remedy hereof, I hope they will not be Lazy or Indiſcreet, either in the Choiſe of ſit Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to repreſent them, nor in ſoliciting them to have things done for the Common Intereſt of the Crown and People; Remembring all Men are Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and nothing but their Works follow them to their Grave, and after Death comes Judgment. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43472:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
